But I'm here to tell you about my son's
story and the horrific experience that he
went through. First of all, I want you to
get to know my boy. This is my Jake, my
baby boy, one out of my two kids. And, oh,
those dimples. Everyone commented on those
cute little dimples. I was this fifth
grade teacher, which every kid's
nightmare, right? To have your mom as your
teacher. But I was this fifth grade
teacher, so I was able to see what a kind
-hearted, thoughtful, and caring kid this
was. Not just as a mother, but as a
teacher. I remember one day after school,
he came up to me and he kind of had glassy
eyes, you know, almost teary. And he said,
I said, what's wrong? And he said, mom,
something happened today. And first I need
to give you a little background. We had a
little boy in our class that had a medical
issue that didn't have control of his
vowels and oftentimes he smelled and the
kids really made fun of him. He had no
friends. He was picked on. Don't touch
these guy cooties type stuff. And Jake was
his friend. Jake had a group of friends
that he hung out with that he loved and
they loved him, but he saw this little boy
and he befriended him. And after school
one day he came up to me and he said, Mom,
he said, they're being so mean to Brian.
And I said, I said, what happened? He
said, well, at school at recess. He said,
I said, come on, Brian, let's go out. And
we were walking out on the playground and
my friends were like on the basketball
court and saying, Jake, come over, come
play with us. And he's like, yeah, let's
go play. Come on, Brian, let's go play.
And we got over there and they said, just
you, Jake, not Brian. And I said, well,
Jake, what did you do? How did you handle
that? And he said, I just turned to him
and I said, nah, it's okay. Brian and I
are going to go play over here. And so he
actually gave up his friends because he
saw this little boy I had no friends.
That's the kind of kid my Jake was.
When he was in middle school, he would
spend his days off. He'd say, mom, can I
go to school with you? And even in high
school, mom, can I go to school with you
on his days off? And he would come to
school with me and he would help tutor the
kids. He would help them with math or he'd
read to them. The kids in my class always
knew Jake.
Jake loved donuts. This was his last
birthday. I made him a cake out of donuts
and he said, Mom, that was the best cake
ever. He also loved about the donuts every
year when he was in high school and he had
his own money. He would show up on my
birthday and he would show up with three
dozen donuts so he could give donuts to my
class for my birthday. That's the kind of
kid Jake was. He also was an animal lover.
This was his best buddy Bosco and he loved
dogs. He loved animals.
He also loved music. When he was a little
toddler, he'd be in the backseat. It was
amazing because I'm big into music, so I'd
have the music blaring and he'd be in the
backseat as a toddler in his little car
seat going to the beat of the music. Just
even as a little toddler, he loved music.
He loved everything and a big variety. He
loved Linkin Park all the way to Elvis and
Buddy Holly and I was like, wow, that's a
huge, huge thing. One of my sweet memories
is on Mother's Day, he bought me tickets
to the Styx REO Speedwagon concert, but it
wasn't for me to take just anyone. He gave
me one ticket and the other one was for
him. And we went as mother and son and
rocked out to Stug's and REO Speedwagon.
That's the kind of kid Jake was. He was a
great student. He got his associate's
degree while he was in high school, which
was a great achievement for him. Most of
all, Jake loved his family. My two nephews
were Jake's best friends and they did
everything together, including pranking
me. That was their most favorite thing to
do. And then I got my first grandbaby and
that just made Jake an uncle and he was so
proud to be Uncle Jake now.
Sorry, I'm having issues. Okay.
Jake and I had the fall break and so we
went on a road trip together. Just the two
of us. And we went to the Grand Canyon. We
went to Bryce and just had mother and son
time. These are the pictures. from our
road trip as well as the one that's up
here. This one he had never seen the Grand
Canyon and when we got there it was full
of clouds and so that was his picture with
the Grand Canyon was clouds in the
background. This right here was our last
trip together. Two weeks later is where
I'm going to pick up with the story.
It was the day before Halloween and I was
a teacher and I had a teacher work day and
I was sitting at my desk when I got a call
from the Millow County Police Department.
I said, is this Cindy George? And I said,
yes. And he said, do you have a son named
Jake? Jake? And I said, yes. And do you
have a place in Kanosh, Utah? And I said,
yes. And that hit me. Jake's at our little
place. We had just little getaway place
there and he must have he must be there
and they must think that he's breaking in
or something like that. And I said, yes.
Yeah, that's my son. And they said, he has
taken his life. in your home.
I just argued with him. I said, you got
the wrong kid. My kid was not on drugs. My
kid did not drink. My kid was not
depressed. This did not make sense. It
couldn't be my kid. And I argued with him
until they described his car and explained
that he had taken a gun and he was gone.
The rest of the day was kind of a blur.
And why? Couldn't even fathom how this
could happen. And they the police
department, they faxed a couple of his
letters. He wrote seven letters. This is
kind of kid Jake was. He wrote letters to
his sister, to his friends, to his nephews
or his cousins. This one's to me. I'm just
going to read part of it. It says, Dear
Mom, I love you so much and it pains me to
write this. I wish I could live with what
I did. I know this will be hard for you,
but I need you to continue on with your
life. I hope you don't think too bad of me
for what I did. I know this is sudden, but
the hell that I went through Sunday
through Thursday was too much for me to
handle. I love you dearly, mom. You will
always be my mother and I will always be
your baby boy. But, Jake, it still didn't
make sense. What could possibly make him
do this? And so four months later, the
police department gave me back his phone
and the last letter that they held. And it
says, my dear, this is poor.
all of his parents. I'm sorry for what I
have done, but I have nothing to live for
anymore. I have made a huge mistake that I
can't live with. Look at my phone and read
the messages that are in the Kik app.
Start with the girl profile named Alona
Home and then move on to the profile just
for fun. These messages will explain
everything. From Sunday to Thursday, my
life has been a living hell and
rollercoaster of emotion. The one person
that owns these two profiles will be using
Facebook to ruin my life. There's a good
chance I will lose my job and get kicked
out of school as the person attacks me
there using Facebook. I urge you all to
control what happens on Facebook as much
as possible. This person claims that they
will copy some of your profiles and attack
your friends also. This person attacked my
three most important things being my
school, my job, and my family.
Please don't change your lives for me.
Hold your children and grandchildren
close. I love you all. Jake. So, I'm just
going to take you a little timeline.
I got his phone back and I read. I just
took it aside and I read the whole
conversation. And I understood the
pressure and the hell that they put him
through. This happened in five days. I was
with him on Sunday and Friday. He was
gone.
I read the conversation how the predator
talked him into sending him a nude photo.
After grooming him, they talked him into
sending one nude photo. And kind of like,
I'll send you one, you send me one. Talked
him into it. I saw the high pressure that
they put him in. And then I saw how they
sent him names of family members and said,
we're going after them next. And I think
that's where it put Jake over the edge. So
I'm going to take you a timeline what his
life went through in five days. on Sunday
they get him to send after grooming they
got him to move to the Kik app I'm not
sure where the original source came from
because he was on some dating sites and he
was on Facebook I believe it came from
Facebook but I'm not sure on that but they
got him to move to the Kik app which is
common
or this type of a thing After they got him
to move, they said, now we've got you. Or
after they got him to send a picture, they
said, now we've got you. Just added and
saved all your Facebook friends on my
laptop. I am going to send them your nude
photo and post it all over your friends'
Facebook timeline and also to your job on
UPS Facebook page. But I will not do that
if you send me the money right now, okay?
After constant threats, high pressure, get
there, get to the Walmart, get an
application. Let me see the application.
Get to the ATM. Let me see the money. He
was having to take pictures of everything.
They were on him. Just didn't give him
time to even process and think this
through. He finally at 7.06 that night, he
makes a payment of $300 at a Walmart at
Saratoga Springs to a Marie's Abril in the
Philippines. Then Jake asks for her to
please delete the picture like you said.
This was the response he got. he said,
they said, do you know what a genie is,
Jake? And he said, yes. He says, well, you
are my genie today and I have found you.
So you have to grant me three wishes. And
he says, which are, which you means you're
going to have to make three payments.
After begging for her to leave him alone,
saying, I'm just a college kid, please
leave me alone. Jake ends up back at
Walmart that night to make another payment
of $130. The torment and constant threats
continued for the next few days. Jake paid
them everything he had, $680. And after
fulfilling the three wishes that she
required of him, Jake then begged her to
now please delete the photo.
And the reply was, you
work at UPS. In two weeks, you'll have
another paycheck. And Jake realized this
is never going to end.
He says, please delete it. I can't live
the next two weeks with you blackmailing
me. I gave you his total that he had just
given his last payment. And he said, he
said, you won't get any more money if I'm
not here.
The reply was, five guys committed suicide
because I posted their nudes and ruined
their life, but I never care because it's
their choice, not mine. You will be the
sixth and I still won't care. On Thursday,
Jake buys a garden hose. and heads at a
Home Depot in American Fork. And then in
Richfield, he buys a ream of paper and a
box of envelopes and he goes to a hotel.
And I assume that's where he wrote all of
his letters. And he left one on the desk
in the hotel saying the person that was in
this room is going to take their life.
Please contact. And he said Brandon
George, which was my husband at the time,
his brother that lived in Kanash and said,
please contact him. I'm going to be out in
the West Desert.
Then on his way out of town, he bought a
helium tank, which was later found empty
in his car. Along with when I got in his
car, I found the hose and it was black on
one end. And the helium tank was empty.
And I think that he tried to take his life
using that method. And I think it was just
taking too long and he could not do it.
and he knew that my husband at the time
had a shotgun in Kanosh and he found the
key and he took his life. The hell that I
go through thinking of those last moments
as he's sitting there in so much torment
and having to pull that trigger because of
these evil people and what they did. No
mother should have to bury their son. And
it was so pointless.
I could not catch this person. I was told
because it came from the Philippines,
there was nothing that could be done.
There's a program on the National
Geographic called Trafficking with Mariana
Van Zeller. They contacted me out of the
blue. I don't know how they found me. And
they said, we want to do your son's story.
And we want to go to the Philippines and
try and find who did this. And so she came
to my house. They did the interview. And
then they proceeded to investigate. And
they found the source in the Philippines.
And it was a call center. A huge call
center. This is going on and hitting so
many of our children. It's a big business
there.
She actually talked to one of the people
that does this and he was hooded so all
you could see was his eyes. She said, do
you know that people are killing
themselves because of that? And he said,
yeah, I watched one of them do it. That's
the kind of evil we're talking about here.
Something has to be done. Brandon Guffey,
a state representative in South Carolina
that I have spoken to, had lost his son
Gavin, his 17-year-old son Gavin, to sex
extortion. And after his son died, he
actually got contact. He was contacted by
the perpetrator. And they sent him a
laughing emoji. And it said, did I tell
you your son begged for his life? That's
the kind of evil we're talking about here.
This is coming from Nigeria. This is
coming from the Ivory Coast. This is
coming from here. We need to do something
to warn these kids. I cannot catch the
people that did this to my son. Brandon
Guffey, I saw on his Facebook about six
months ago, he and his wife were holding a
set of handcuffs on his page. And they
have Gavin's name etched in the in his
handcuffs. And they went to Nigeria and
they found who did this to their son. And
they extradited them and they've been
charged. What a great thing that they were
able to do that. The Philippine government
were not so accommodating when the
National Geographic went over there. They
know who started the whole thing in the
Philippines and she's been arrested and
then let out.
I asked for your help because I can't
catch them. My son died so needlessly. I
can't catch them, but the only thing I can
do is warn others. Please talk to your
grandkids, your kids, your neighbors, your
nephews. Talk to them so they won't take
the bait. That's the only thing we can do
is educate so they won't take the bait.
And we need to also talk to them and let
them know no matter what, no matter what
is happening in your life, that they can
come to you. I wish Jake would have been
able to come to me. I wish I could have
comforted him and said, it's okay, they
can't destroy your life with a picture.
Don't ever think this This can never
happen to my child, my nephew, because I
can testify to you that it can happen to
the best of kids. Thank you. Thank you.